Iakov Markov

Prague, Czech Republic+420 608-375-392iakovmarkov@gmail.com

Software Engineer

Summary

I'm a seasoned Software Engineer with solid understanding of web applications and services, with main focus on front-end technologies and experienced in building B2B applications for global market. I focus on delivering best user experience to customers while striving for elegant and clean solution on the inside.

I'm also interested in other spheres of information technology like IoT, BI or Big Data. I enjoy trying out exotic languages and concepts, and applying them to my daily work.

Work experience

Front-End Team Leader

March 2017 - Present

Ataccama Software - Prague, Czechia

As a team leader I was responsible for a wide array of tasks - from evaluating of potential colleagues to creating high-level architecture. I was providing long-term vision in terms of technologies and techniques choice, as well as short-term assistance with building performant and reusable components. I coordinated development of front-end between four SCRUM teams, making sure those teams stick to the existing architecture, reuse each other's code and make a product with world-class UX.

I was also playing a role of a SCRUM-master for one 6-people SCRUM team and mentoring two junior-level front-end developers.

Accomplishments:

- Streamlined onboarding process for new colleagues by writing guides and documentation;
- Coordinated efforts of 4 teams working on the same codebase;
- Introduced different tools like error reporting, A/B testing, session playback and others;

Front-End Engineer

September 2016 - March 2017

Ataccama Software - Prague, Czechia

When starting as a senior front-end engineer at Ataccama, I was presented with a product that was in development for approximately 5 months. My main tasks were developing new features and making sure existing ones are smooth like butter.

Accomplishments:

- Implemented WebSocket-based communication channel between front-end and back-end, enabling real-time updates of data;
- Optimized performance of key parts of application leading to better user experience;
- Laid groundwork for translating application into other languages including strings, dates and number formats;

Front-End Developer

June 2015 - September 2016

ViewWorld - Copenhagen, Denmark

I've worked on supporting a legacy solution built on Backbone.js with Ruby on Rails templates as well as building custom dashboards for ViewWorld clients like Vodafone Foundation, AVSI and others. The dashboards were single-page applications that presented data collected and stored in ViewWorld with varying degree of interactivity.

Accomplishments:

• Updated critical components in a 4 year old codebase;

Front-End Developer

European Experts - Prague, Czechia

I've worked as a single front-end developer on a complex CRM built to support company's recruitment process. It was an single-page application built on React.js and Reflux. Because of extremely limited resources, I opted to use some open-source React and jQuery components like modals, typeaheads, alert windows and others. It proved to be a great way to build a MVP, but we had to gradually phase out those parts of the application in favor of our own, much more stable components. Most of the communication with back-end is handled by RESTful API, with some parts of the application using WebSocket protocol for real-time communication.

Accomplishments:

• Implemented MVP and later on developed it into production quality as a sole front-end developer;

Web Developer

October 2014 - December 2015

Fairpeople - Prague, Czechia

I started working on a Fairpeople Online project - a website that provided small businesses in CIS countries with affordable and easy-to-use websites. My main responsibility was building our web application and automating tasks like domain registration, hosting account & database creation, CMS and template deployment and other similar routine procedures.

The web application was built on WordPress with a custom responsive template on it. Our visitors were able to choose a domain name, one of preselected website templates and a few additional features like multi-language support or e-shop, place and order and pay. Then the application registered a domain using our partner registrar, created a hosting account on our servers using ISP Manager API and deployed a WordPress installation with pre-installed theme and plugins.

Accomplishments:

• Automated the whole process of creating a website for our customers;

Freelancer & Consultant

2013 - Present

I've started my career as a freelance web developer. My focus was mainly on building clean and responsive websites using popular open-source CMSs like WordPress, Joomla, Drupal and ModX. I've quickly studied and learned to apply numerous plugins and libraries available online, and later started writing my own, providing great level of customization to my customers.

Later on, I transitioned to more mature technologies and started providing my clients with completely custom-built solutions, again using open-source technologies like Laravel, Ruby on Rails and React.

I'm still doing occasional freelance work, mainly when getting clients referred to me by friends, colleagues and other happy customers.

I treat freelance work as a great opportunity to get my hands on new technologies and to apply some of that knowledge to my main project.

Skills

Front-End Technologies

- JavaScript
 - ES6 and beyond
- React.js
 - Redux
 - Redux-saga, redux-
 - Reflux and other Flux implementations
 - Reselect, Recompose, other helper libraries

- CSS-in-JS libraries like Fela
- SASS, LESS
- CSS methodologies: BEM, SMACSS

- Webpack, babel, gulp
- REST APIs
- Websockets
- Backbone.js
- D3.js
- RxIS
- Elm

Programming Languages

- Node.js
 - Express.js
- Java
 - Java SE
 - Spring
 - Hibernate
- PHP
 - WordPress
 - Laravel
- Ruby, Rails
- Databases and SQL
 - PostgreSQL
 - MySQL

General Technical Skills

- Linux
 - Daily power user
 - Web servers setup & administration

- GIT
- Docker
- Nginx
- Adobe CS

Education

Czech Technical University in Prague

2013 - 2016

My studies at CTU gave a solid knowledge of Java, understanding of multiple programming patterns and anti-patterns and experience leading team projects. However I had to support myself financially and haven't got my degree, instead focusing on pursuing a career.

Ural Polytechnical College

2008 - 2012

During my studies at Ural Polytechnical College I've gained a solidoverview of IT that gave me a good understanding and solid basis for my career. My final coursework was a web application that verified student's homework - essentially compiled and ran a program, fed it input and verified the output, displaying the results in the web browser.

Hobbies & Interests

- Weightlifting
- Electric guitar
- Traveling
- Horology